Guide to the Cornell Eleven records and briefs, 1979-1984.
Cornell Eleven records and briefs
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Cornell Eleven records and briefs, 1979-1984.
4197
Cornell Eleven.
21 cubic ft.
Correspondence, newspapers, publications, reports.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Files relating to the sex discrimination case, including files of J. Anthony Gaenslen (attorney for the plaintiffs) and Jennie Farley.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The case, brought by a group of women calling themselves the Cornell Eleven (Cornell 11) and including Donna Zahorik, Judith Long Laws, Jacqueline Livingston, Antonia Glasse, and Charlotte Farris, accused Cornell University of academic sex-biased evaluation procedures.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Files relating to the sex discrimination case, including files of J. Anthony Gaenslen (attorney for the plaintiffs) and Jennie Farley.
Three volume typescript copy of briefs and trial records from a court case, Donna Zahorik, Judith Long Laws, Jacqueline Livingston, Antonia Glasse, and Charlotte Farris, Plaintiffs v. Cornell University, seeking that the action be maintained as a class action for "all women with academic appointments who are employed by Cornell University..." Also one Cornell Eleven t-shirt.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cornell Eleven.; Farley, Jennie.; Farris, Charlotte J.; Gaenslen, J. Anthony.; Glasse, Antonia.; Laws, Judith Long.; Livingston, Jacqueline.; Zahorik, Donna.; Bond, Schoeneck & King.; Cornell University.; Hogan & Hartson.
Subjects:
Sex discrimination in employment.; Sex discrimination in education.; Women in education.; Women college teachers.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Restricted until 2031.
CONTAINER LIST
- Undescribed material (Box 1-14, 21)
- Court Papers, Plaintiffs’ opposition to defendant’s motion for summary judgment, working papers – memos, affidavits, exhibits., n.d. (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Rajender v. University of Minnesota, No. 4-73-435 (D.Minn) 1980 – copy of the consent decree., [1980] (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Settlement proposal – Draft of the settlement proposal, notes, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Friends of the Cornell Eleven (support to the Cornell Eleven Case) – Pamphlets, correspondence, petitions, paper clippings, notes, drafts of statements., 1980-1981 (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Friends of the Cornell Eleven, gift appeal., [1983] (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Memorandum of law in support of motion for class determination – notice of motion, motion., 1982 (Box 15, Folder 7)
- List of names and those who suggested them by department or school. Documentation on academic women and sex discrimination., n. d. (Box 15, Folder 8)
- Processing complaints; perspective on affirmative action – Copy of a report on processing complaints of discrimination on the basis of sex (1977) and study untitled A perspective on affirmative action (Ann S. Bedingfield, seminar in legal education, 1980), 1977-1980 (Box 15, Folder 9)
- Women faculty – articles, pamphlet., 1979-1980 (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Women faculty; psychological studies – Articles., 1975-1981 (Box 15, Folder 11)
- AAUW (American Association of University Women), publications and newspapers – report, gift appeal, newspapers., 1978-1982 (Box 15, Folder 12)
- Academic appraisal – articles, notes., 1980-1984 (Box 15, Folder 13)
- Faculty appointments in Cornell University – extracts from directories and reports, memos, notes, article., 1979-1984 (Box 15, Folder 14)
- “Sex discrimination by law: a study in judicial perspective” by John D. Johmston Jr. and Charles L. Knapp., 1971 (Box 15, Folder 15)
- Appointments in Cornell University in 1979 – statistics., 1979 (Box 15, Folder 16)
- Information about Louise Palmer Fortmann – note, CV, letter. Affirmative action statements about academic appointments in 1980 – statistics., 1980-1981 (Box 15, Folder 17)
- Discrimination, Articles: “Wage discrimination, Job Segregation, and Title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964” by Ruth G. Blumrosen; “Academic freedom and problem of proof” by Karl Boedecker., 1979-1980 (Box 15, Folder 18)
- Women faculty in Cornell university – notes, paper clippings, statistics., 1978-1979 (Box 15, Folder 19)
- Women at Cornell; Meetings of the Friends of the Cornell Eleven; sex discrimination – statistics, notes, minutes, article clippings, letters., 1980-1982 (Box 15, Folder 20)
- Strategies to prevent claims against universities on employment subjects – articles., 1973-1981 (Box 15, Folder 21)
- Sex discrimination’s legal aspects – articles, notes., 1975-1981 (Box 15, Folder 22)
- “The status of women at the city university of New York”, a report of the Chancellor’s advisory committee on the status of women at the city university of New York, 1972., 1981 (Box 15, Folder 23)
- Digest of Education statistics., 1979-1980 (Box 15, Folder 24)
- Report of the Ad Hoc trustee Committee on the Status of Women at Cornell., 1974 (Box 15, Folder 25)
- Review and recommendations concerning affirmative action in selected departments, colleges and divisions, Cornell University (report by the Task Force on implementation to the affirmative Action Advisory Board)., 1979 (Box 15, Folder 26)
- Promoting and achieving sex equity in vocational education, report of a project conducted by the National Center for Research in Vocational education)., 1979 (Box 15, Folder 27)
- Academic Appointees in Cornell University – 1 volume of statistics., 1980 (Box 15, Folder 28)
- Exhibits to defendant Cornell University’s memorandum of points and authorities in opposition to plaintiff’s motion for class determination – draft version., [1982] (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Cornell Eleven – papers clippings, articles., 1980-1981 (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Cornell Eleven’s case, documentation collected by Jennifer Farley – legal papers, correspondence, paper clippings, drafts of settlement proposals, statistics., 1975-1982 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- “A preliminary statement on judicially compelled disclosure in the nonrenewal of faculty appointments” – copy of the article., 1981 (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Correspondence from Hogan & Hartson – Letters and inclosed documentation., 1984 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Plaintiffs’ supplemental opposition to defendant’s motion for summary judgment – draft., [1984] (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Deposition of K. C. Parsons – draft. (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Tracing salary cursus. – notes, statistics., 1984 (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Questions to ask about trusts and their tax consequences – list of questions. (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Letter of Irving Lazar to C. Farris explaining the reasons of his refusal to recommend her promotion., 1979 (Box 16, Folder 10)
- Cornell University’s salary studies – letter, rosters, graphs and histograms (no. 1-90)., 1976-1984 (Box 16, Folder 13-23)
  - Nos. 1-4 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - No. 5 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Nos. 6-10 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Nos. 16-26 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - No. 27 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Nos. 32-39 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Nos. 40-47 (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Nos. 50-77 (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - Nos. 78-85 (Box 16, Folder 21)
  - Nos. 86-89 (Box 16, Folder 22)
  - No. 90 (Box 16, Folder 23)
- Articles and studies: extract from an article about discrimination; comment on manuscript evaluation procedure; “Impression on affirmative action in 1978: a report to the German Marshall Fund” by Sadie Roberts., 1972-1978 (Box 16, Folder 24)
- Defendant Cornell University’s supplemental memorandum of points and authorities in opposition to plaintiff’s motion for class determination., n. d. (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Exhibit of academic staff from 1976-1980., [1981] (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Charlotte Farris files – listings, correspondence, memos, statements, notes, publishing agreement, bills, evaluations, statements, affidavits., 1978-1980 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Judith Long Laws files – listings, correspondence, memos, curriculum vitae, statement, notes, survey, evaluations, chronology, copies of court papers., 1975-1981 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Antonia Glasse files – listings, correspondence, memos, guidelines, paper clipping, evaluations, statements, legal papers, curriculum vitae, articles., 1963-1981 (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Jacqueline Livingston file – listing, petition, correspondence, evaluations, notes, memos, meeting minutes, chronology, curriculum vitae., 1976-1980 (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Donna Zahorik files – listings, correspondence, memos, meeting minutes, legal papers, statements, curriculum vitae, notes, resolution, surveys, articles, evaluations, 1975-1981 (Box 17, Folder 7)
- Sex discrimination – articles., 1980-1982, n. d. (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Faculty women and faculty couples in Cornell University – Affidavit, statistics, memos, notes, correspondence, drafts of arguments., 1978-1982, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 9)
- Advance response to the first interrogatory set in “Plaintiff’s interrogatories Re: Plaintiffs’ response to defendant’s opposition to motion for class determination” – correspondence, questionnaires., 1981 (Box 17, Folder 10)
- Cooke deposition – notes., n. d. (Box 17, Folder 11)
- Plaintiff’s supplemental opposition to defendant’s motion for summary judgment, working file – draft., n. d. (Box 17, Folder 12)
- Settlement, working file – notes, letter., 1982-1983 (Box 17, Folder 13)
- Fundraising, working file – notes, correspondence, listing, pamphlets, statements., 1983-1984 (Box 17, Folder 14)
- Title VII and sex discrimination – articles., 1977-1980, n. d. (Box 18, Folder 1)
- Cases involving institution of higher education being sued by women faculty – filing cards., n. d. (Box 18, Folder 2)
- Information about faculty members and their salaries from 1976-1980 – filing cards., [after 1980] (Box 18, Folder 3)
- Class correspondents of Cornell Alumni News – filing cards., 1981-1982 (Box 18, Folder 4)
- New appointees from 1973-1976 by level, sex, and inclusion in 1981-1982 staff directory – filing cards., n. d. (Box 18, Folder 5)
- Faculty members by title from February, 1977 thru February 1981 – filing cards., n. d. (Box 18, Folder 6)
- References of articles and cases – filing cards and box., n. d. (Box 18, Folder 7)
- Men and women assistant professors at Ithaca Campus, Cornell University, as of Fall, 1971 – filing cards., n. d. (Box 18, Folder 8)
- Assistant professors appointed in 1973-1974 – filing cards., n. d. (Box 18, Folder 9)
- Assistant professors appointed in 1974-1975 – filing cards, n. d. (Box 18, Folder 10)
- Women considered for tenure turned down by a negative department vote in 1976-1977., n. d. (Box 18, Folder 11)
- Names of people considered too early or gotten out of Fall 1981 Directory., n. d. (Box 18, Folder 12)
- Mailing list., n. d. (Box 18, Folder 13)
- List of associate or assistant professors and their departments., n. d. (Box 18, Folder 14)
- Plaintiff’s memorandum of law in support of motion to reconsider court’s letter of August 12, 1983, and grant plaintiffs full rule 56(f) discovery or in the alternative to decide the motion for summary judgment – salary claims – on the papers already before the court – original version., 1983 (Box 19, Folder 1)
- Plaintiffs’ opposition to defendant’s motion for summary judgment (salary claims) – copy of the court volume with a court stamp., 1983 (Box 19, Folder 2)
- Working file for a meeting – note, letters, article clippings, documentation, settlement proposal., [1982] (Box 19, Folder 3)
- Defendant Cornell University’s memorandum of points and authorities in opposition to plaintiffs’ motion for class determination – annotated copy of vol. 3., [1983] (Box 20, Folder 1)
- Defendant Cornell University’s supplemental memorandum of points and authorities in opposition to plaintiffs’ motion for class determination., [1983] (Box 20, Folder 2)
- Plaintiffs’ reply to defendant’s opposition to plaintiffs’ motion for class determination – copy of the vol. 6 of court papers including a court stamp and the form for a stipulation. (Box 20, Folder 3)
- Settlement of the Cornell Eleven case in the press – clippings of newspapers., 1984 (Box 20, Folder 4)
- Copy of the Cornell Chronicle, vol. 13, no. 18., 1982 (Box 20, Folder 5)
- Plaintiffs’ replay to defendant’s opposition to plaintiffs’ motion for class determination – copy of an annotated draft., [1983] (Box 20, Folder 6)
- Copy of the Communiqué, no. of June, 1981., 1981 (Box 20, Folder 7)
- Resolving sex discrimination on campus: four perspectives. Ed. Jennie Farley., [1982?] (Box 20, Folder 8)
- Cornell Eleven case and sex discrimination, clippings of articles., 1980-1984 (Box 20, Folder 9)